[MUSIC]
[음악]
Let's start by discussing some areas in which recommender systems are playing
먼저 추천 시스템이 보이지 않는 곳에서
a really active role behind the scenes.
적극적인 역할을 담당하는 분야를 소개하죠
And as we're gonna see in this discussion, depending on the specific application
이 논의에서 보겠지만 분야에 따라
different aspects of the objective we're trying to optimize are gonna be important.
최적화하려는 목표의 여러 면이 중요해집니다
But before we start talking about recommenders systems,
추천 시스템을 논하기 전에
it's really important to talk about the idea of personalization,
개인화란 개념에 대해 알아보는 게 중요합니다
because personalization is transforming our experience of the world.
개인화가 사용자 경험을 일변시키고 있기 때문인데요
As we talked about in the clustering and similarity module, there are lots and
클러스터링과 유사도 모듈에서 알아봤듯이
lots of articles out there.
세상에는 수많은 글이 있습니다
In lots and lots of webpages.
수많은 웹페이지 속에요
And we can't possibly be expected to browse all of them.
모든 페이지를 들어가보는 건 불가능합니다
So another example here is YouTube.
또 다른 예는 유투브입니다
So YouTube,
유투브에는
it's quoted that there are roughly 100 hours of video recorded per minute.
대략 비디오 100시간 분량이 매분 업로드된다고 하죠
And the question is what do I care about.
그럼 뭘 봐야 하냐는 게 문젭니다
You know, I go on YouTube and I wanna watch some video that's of interest to me.
유투브에서 관심 갈만한 비디오를 보고 싶습니다
So this is an example, clearly, of information overload.
이건 분명히 정보 과다이지요
There's just way too much content there for me possibly to be able to go and for
누군가 도와주지 않고서야 관심가는 컨텐츠를
me to find what I'm interested in without somebody helping that content come to me.
찾아낼 수 없습니다
So browsing, the traditional form of browsing, is history.
직접 둘러보면서 찾는 건 이미 과거의 유물이죠
There needs to be some way in which
나한테 맞는 컨텐츠를 자동으로 발견할
the content that's relevant to me is automatically discovered.
방법이 있어야 합니다
And so this the notion of personalization, where we wanna connect users like myself,
이게 개인화의 개념이며 이렇게 저와 같은 사용자와
who goes to YouTube and items which, in this case,
유투브 비디오와 같은 항목의
are gonna be videos on YouTube need to somehow be connected.
연결이 필요한 것입니다
Okay, so,
이렇게
personalization is gonna play a key role in this notion of recommender systems and
추천 시스템에서는 개인화가 핵심적인 역할을 합니다
now let's talk about some examples where recommender systems are very important.
추천 시스템이 아주 중요한 예를 더 들어봅시다
So one very classic example that we mentioned a little bit earlier was this
고전적인 예는 앞서 이야기했듯이
idea of Netflix where, here people go and they watch videos.
비디오 유통업체인 넷플릭스의 발상입니다
And Netflix has this goal of trying to make suggestions of which movies or
넷플릭스에게는 사용자들의 관심을 살만한
TV shows might be of interest the person who's come to this site.
영화, TV쇼를 추천한다는 목표가 있습니다
And the question is, how are we gonna go about doing these recommendations.
그렇다면 어디서부터 시작해야 할까요?
Another example, again going back to something we talked about earlier,
이전에 말씀드린 바와 같이 또 다른 예는
is Amazon making product recommendations.
아마존의 상품 추천입니다
So you go on to Amazon, you purchase some product, and you'll see on the site that
아마존에 가서 상품을 구입하면
it makes a recommendation of other products you might be interested in.
관심이 갈만한 상품 추천 목록이 뜹니다
But one important thing to incorporate in these recommendations
추천에서 유의해야 할 점은
is the fact that not only do you have to take into account
한 세션의 관심사만
the interest that the person had in this one session.
고려해서는 안 된다는 것입니다
So for example here we're showing that somebody bought a book about websites and
예를 들어 누군가 웹사이트에 관한 책을 사면
might be interested in another book about web applications or for
웹 애플리케이션에 관한 또 다른 책에,
example my most recent purchase on Amazon were shoes for my son but
제 최근 아마존 이력에 아들 신발이 있는데
the interest that I have in making that purchase of shoes isn't my only interest.
그렇다고 신발만이 유일한 관심 상품은 아닙니다
I'm not only looking for shoes for a one-year old.
한 살짜리를 위한 신발만 찾는 게 아니죠
There are lots of other reasons why I go to Amazon and make purchases.
아마존에서 구입을 하는 데는 수많은 이유가 있습니다
And if you look at my history of purchases you're gonna be able to make much
구매 이력을 보면 한 세션만을
better recommendations for me than just based on a single session.
근거로 삼는 것보다 훨씬 나은 추천을 할 수 있죠
And likewise, recommendations might change over time.
이와 같이 추천은 시간에 따라 변합니다
So there's interest in making recommendations, for example,
오늘 사고 싶을만한 상품에 대한
what I might be interested in purchasing today.
추천을 하는 데도 의미가 있습니다
So if you look at my purchase history a year ago,
일 년 전 구매 이력을 보면
I was buying a lot of newborn products.
신생아 상품을 엄청 샀다는 걸 알게 되겠죠
So newborn baby products.
신생아를 위한 유아용품
But that's probably not something that I'm very likely to purchase today.
하지만 오늘 신생아 상품을 사려고는 하지 않을 겁니다
So the recommendations that Amazon presents to me today
아마존이 제게 보여주는 추천은
have to adapt with time.
시간에 따라 조정되어야 합니다
So just as on demand video with personalized recommendation has really
개인화 추천이 포함된 주문형 비디오가
revolutionized how people watch movies and TV shows, likewise there are a lot
사람들의 영화, TV쇼 시청 방식에 혁신을 가져왔듯이
of websites that provide streaming audio with personal recommendations.
음악 스트리밍 사이트는 개인에 맞는 추천을 합니다
However, in this case unlike thinking about on demand video
하지만 이 경우 주문형 비디오와 달리
here we want one song to play after another.
현재 듣는 곡 다음에 나올 곡을 골라야 하죠
And what we want is we want some coherent stream of songs.
음악에 일관성이 있어야 합니다
So songs I've liked I wanna play similar songs.
좋아하는 곡과 비슷한 곡을 듣고 싶어하죠
I don't wanna rapidly switch between for example some cafe Indi songs,
카페에서 들을만한 인디 음악을 듣다
all of a sudden playing a heavy metal song.
뜬금없이 헤비메탈로 넘어가고 싶지는 않을 겁니다
But at the same time
하지만 동시에 방금 들은 곡을
I don't want a song I just heard to play again and again and again.
반복해서 듣고 싶지도 않습니다
So I want some sense of recommendations that are coherent but
그러므로 일관성을 유지하면서
I also want them to provide a diverse sequence of songs for me to listen to.
다양한 노래 목록을 제공했으면 합니다
Okay, well another critical area where recommender systems have
추천 시스템이 결정적 역할을 한
played a very active role is in social networking.
또 다른 분야는 소셜 네트워킹입니다
So for example on Facebook there are tons and tons of users.
예를 들어 페이스북에서는 무수한 사용자가 있죠
And we wanna form connections between these users.
사용자 간의 연결을 구축해야 합니다
So for example here might be a graph of connections between users on Facebook and
페이스북 사용자 사이의 연결 그래프인데
maybe I'm this pink node right here, and
제가 여기 있는 핑크색 노드라고 하죠
Facebook wants to recommend other people I might be interested in connecting with.
페이스북은 제가 친구가 되고 싶어할만한 사람을 추천하려고 하겠죠
In this application and it's important to note that both the users and
여기에서는 사용자와 '항목'이 같다는 사실에
the quote unquote items are of the same type.
주목해야 합니다
We're both people.
우리는 모두 사람입니다
So when I'm a user on Facebook the things that are being recommended to me,
그리고 제가 페이스북에 있을 때
the items, they are other people.
추천되는 항목 또한 사람들입니다
So we're gonna end up with users and
그러므로 사용자와 항목은 이 영역에선
items being exactly the same type in this application.
동일하게 되죠
But the recommendation system that we've talked about have really focused on
지금까지는 온라인 미디어에 초점을 맞춘
online media.
추천 시스템에 대해 알아봤습니다
But more and more, people are realizing other area's in which recomender systems
시간이 갈수록 다른 분야에서도 추천 시스템이
can play a really important role.
중요한 역할을 한다는 사실이 드러나고 있습니다
And just as one example,
예를 하나 들자면
we can think about what is call drug-target interactions.
약물-표적 상호관계가 있습니다
And here, maybe we have some drug that's been studied, for example,
어떤 약물이 연구되었다고 하죠
let's talk about aspirin.
아스피린을 예로 들겠습니다
It's been well studied as a treatment for headaches.
두통 치료제로 철저히 연구되었습니다
But what if it's discovered to have some other possible use?
다른 사용법이 발견된다면 어떨까요?
So for example, for blood thinning, for heart patients?
예를 들어 심장병 환자를 위한 혈액희석제요
If we can find these types of relationships,
이런 관련성을 찾아
if we can repurpose this drug for some other treatment,
다른 치료를 위한 전용이 가능해지면
then that could be really useful, because it's really quite costly and
무척 유용한데 신약에 대한 FDA 승인을
lengthy process to get FDA approval for a completely new drug, but
받는 과정은 길고 고비용이기 때문이죠
if we can take a drug where the types of side effects and
하지만 부작용과 위험성이
the possible risks associated are already well known and well studied.
이미 잘 알려지고 연구된 약물이라면
Then it's a lot easier to get approval for treatment with some other condition,
다른 질환 치료를 위한 승인을 받기가 쉬워집니다
so this is a case where we might say, if you like Aspirin for headaches,
두통에 아스피린이 잘 듣는다면
you might also like Aspirin for your heart condition.
심장질환에도 잘 들을 것이라 추측할 수 있죠
So recommender systems are playing an active role in medicine as just an example
이와 같이 추천 시스템은 의학의 다양한 영역에서
of the diversity of applications where we see these types of systems.
핵심 역할을 하고 있습니다
>> [MUSIC]
[음악]